<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercurius Cambro-Britannicus. Or, Nevvs from Wales, touching the glorious and miraculous propagation of the Gospel in those parts. Being a clear discovery &amp; manifestation of the late invented trade of tith-gathering there, intended by some persons to be suddenly set on foot and established over all England. Well worthy of the serious and timely consideration of the Parliament, Army and nation, and every individual member thereof.</title>
            <author>Griffith, Alexander, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E674_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29650</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E674[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercurius Cambro-Britannicus. Or, Nevvs from Wales, touching the glorious and miraculous propagation of the Gospel in those parts. Being a clear discovery &amp; manifestation of the late invented trade of tith-gathering there, intended by some persons to be suddenly set on foot and established over all England. Well worthy of the serious and timely consideration of the Parliament, Army and nation, and every individual member thereof.</title>
                  <author>Griffith, Alexander, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The authors apologie" signed: M.C.B., i.e. Alexander Griffith.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mercurius Cambro-Britannicus. OR, NEVVS from <hi>WALES,</hi> TOUCHING The Glorious and Miraculous Propagation of the Goſpel in thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>Being a clear DISCOVERY &amp; MANIFESTATION Of the late invented Trade of TITH-GATHERING there, Intended by ſome Perſons to be ſuddenly ſet on foot and eſtabliſhed over all ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Well worthy the ſerious and timely conſideration of the Parliament, Army and Nation, and every individual Member thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 3.7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Return unto me, and I will return unto you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: But ye ſaid, Where ſhall we return? Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me: But ye ſay, Wherein have we robbed thee? In Tythes and Offerings: Ye are curſed with a curſe, for ye have rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me, even this whole nation; bring ye all the Tythes into the ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, that there may be meat in mine houſe; and prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, if I will not open the Windows of heaven, and powr you out a bleſsing, that there ſhal not be room enough to receive it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166287:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166287:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>P. P.</hi> to the indifferent <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſober honeſt <hi>Mercury</hi> coming to my hands, I thought it no great <hi>Error</hi> if I gave it that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment which I ſometimes give even the <hi>Phrantick</hi> Bedlam <hi>Pamphlets:</hi> I muſt confeſſe it was to me a kind of <hi>Eye-ſalve,</hi> for I looked formerly at the wrong end of the <hi>Perſpective,</hi> and the tranſgreſſions of our Welſh <hi>Itinerants,</hi> palliated with the name of <hi>Saints,</hi> ſeemed but ſmall <hi>Atoms</hi> in a large Sun-ſhine. This <hi>Book</hi> is a new <hi>Teleſcope;</hi> it diſcovers what we could not ſee before; and the <hi>Spots</hi> in this Spiritual <hi>Moon,</hi> are <hi>Mountains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe <hi>Saints</hi> have a certain pious <hi>Wawle</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> but out of it they are all <hi>Clutch</hi> and <hi>Claw;</hi> they are as <hi>Lucian</hi> diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered poverty, full of <hi>Hooks;</hi> and they <hi>fiſh</hi> for this <hi>world,</hi> not for that which is to <hi>come:</hi> I did ſometimes <hi>wonder</hi> why they were ſo <hi>buſie</hi> with <hi>South-Wales,</hi> and was about to conſult with the <hi>Map,</hi> if Mount <hi>Sion</hi> were not there: But I underſtand now there is a more <hi>preſent bleſſing</hi> in thoſe parts; there is 20000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> for all the learned Miniſters are ejected; the <hi>Church</hi> is a meer <hi>Carcaſſe,</hi> which makes theſe <hi>Ravens</hi> flock towards it: and now they <hi>flutter</hi> and croak over the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Certainly the Author of this diſcourſe deſerves the <hi>ſuffrages</hi> of all honeſt <hi>men,</hi> and even ſome <hi>Gratulatory returns</hi> and <hi>encouragements</hi> from the <hi>Patrones</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> for in my opinion, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is beholding to him for diſcovering the <hi>Obliquities,</hi> and dark carriages of the <hi>propagators,</hi> who being ſo remote from the <hi>Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance</hi> of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> have made uſe of their <hi>Authority</hi> for their own <hi>private contrivances,</hi> to the diſhonour of their Maſters, and the <hi>Scandal</hi> of true Religion and <hi>piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Army is beholding to him for diſcovering thoſe that ſwallow up that <hi>Treaſure</hi> which ſhould either be employed for the <hi>end</hi> it was <hi>deſigned</hi> by Parliament, or elſe for the payment of their Arrears: Thoſe <hi>men</hi> of <hi>War</hi> that now receive it, having
<pb facs="tcp:166287:3"/>
ſcarce loſt one drop of bloud in the late quarrels, nor had any greater enemy to conteſt withall then <hi>Black-coats,</hi> and the bridge of <hi>Roſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Nation</hi> is indebted to him in making a timely diſcovery of the purpoſe of theſe <hi>Itenerants</hi> to procure the like <hi>Propagation</hi> in all <hi>England,</hi> hoping that the <hi>Parliament</hi> being made ſenſible of the ſad <hi>Conſequences</hi> of this <hi>Itinerary</hi> courſe in <hi>Wales,</hi> may not be ſo eaſily perſwaded to paſſe the like <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>England,</hi> but rather to continue the publique <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God in ſetled <hi>Congregations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. All <hi>Wales</hi> are become <hi>Everlaſting debtors</hi> to him; <hi>For a word ſpoken in ſeaſon is like apples of Gold:</hi> and who knows not but the Lord may encline the hearts of the Parliament to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their future ſupply of <hi>Godly Miniſters</hi> and <hi>School-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> by appointing ſome other <hi>Perſons</hi> by whom the Lord will have his <hi>Work</hi> to be done. And perhaps ſome good men hearing of this <hi>Spiritual famine,</hi> may out of <hi>Charity</hi> come in, and offer themſelves to <hi>labour</hi> in the Lords <hi>Vine-yard,</hi> for the <hi>Harveſt</hi> is great, and the <hi>Labourers</hi> very few.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All the <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Scholers</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are not a little beholding to him: For if this <hi>Itinerary</hi> way of <hi>Congregating per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and <hi>Gathering</hi> of <hi>Churches</hi> ſhould be once ſetled, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted here, there would be little uſe of <hi>Ministers</hi> or <hi>Scholers</hi> in that <hi>expedition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Lawyers</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ought to pay him <hi>Tribute:</hi> For <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>humane learning</hi> are <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Itineraries Principles;</hi> and they hate all <hi>ſtrifes</hi> and <hi>contentions,</hi> other then what ariſe out of their <hi>own Doctrine.</hi> If then, Reader, thou art one of thoſe that would be <hi>undeceived</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſider what thou readeſt: See</hi> how one <hi>Diurnal</hi> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 2. 52. (half whereof is filled up with ſome late news from <hi>Wales</hi>) is <hi>Stig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized</hi> for an <hi>Impoſture</hi> in the very <hi>front</hi> of another of the very <hi>ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ate.</hi>
               </note> give me leave to invite thee to this Book with that <hi>Call</hi> in the <hi>Revelation, Come and ſee.</hi> It is a ſight deſerves thy beſt conſiderations, and the time thou doſt ſpend about it cannot be loſt: Here thou ſhalt ſee the <hi>Wolfe</hi> diveſted of the <hi>Fleece;</hi> thou ſhalt ſee him in his own <hi>Symmetry,</hi> in his own <hi>humours,</hi> without that <hi>Sheepiſh formallity,</hi> that fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent pretended <hi>Perſonated piety,</hi> which he holds forth as a <hi>blind</hi> between him and the world: Here the <hi>Whore</hi> is ſtript of her <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> not ſhee that ſits on <hi>ſeven hills,</hi> but an other more impudent <hi>Whore</hi> that ſits on <hi>ſeven ſcore hills</hi> in <hi>South-walls:</hi> Here thou ſhalt ſee that <hi>Propagation</hi> of the Goſpel, is a <hi>Propagation</hi> of Land and Money; for the <hi>Saints</hi> have advanced from 7. <hi>l. per annum</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:166287:3"/>
1500. <hi>l.</hi> and he who had ſcarce <hi>Frize</hi> for his <hi>breech,</hi> ſtruts it now in <hi>Holy lace</hi> and <hi>Scarlet.</hi> Had their valorous <hi>atchievements</hi> in the <hi>field</hi> gained theſe <hi>goodly things,</hi> as other gallant <hi>Commanders</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> had done, they had been well <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>wealth:</hi> But the <hi>mighty men</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> found a more eaſie and ſafe <hi>way</hi> to attain <hi>both, viz.</hi> by <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>holineſſe,</hi> and <hi>outward form</hi> of <hi>piety,</hi> which hath been no ſmall <hi>advantage</hi> unto them: but I ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear any further mention, becauſe I will not detain thee from the book it ſelf. Read thou the <hi>Truth</hi> and aſſiſt it; for if thou haſt any intereſt in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> it <hi>concernes</hi> thee; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud not the <hi>Diſcoverer</hi> of his juſt <hi>Commendations.</hi> I have no more to trouble thee withall at preſent, unleſſe thou art a <hi>Britan,</hi> if ſo, make true <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> of the two lines under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written,
<q>
                  <l>Da iw'r Kelwydd trâ i Koylîr<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id.</hi> 1 Eſdr. 4.38, 39, 40, 41.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pen elir ym-hell gwell iw'r Gwîr.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="authors_apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:166287:4"/>
            <head>The Authors Apologie.</head>
            <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving been an <hi>eye-witneſs</hi> and <hi>ſpectator</hi> of the ſad deplorable condition of <hi>Southwales,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſince the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for <hi>Propagation</hi> were impowred in thoſe parts, I have not been a little <hi>troubled</hi> with <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>heart</hi> what to do, and how to act and demean my ſelf towards the <hi>perſons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred,</hi> who being many of them my <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> from whom I received <hi>civil reſpects,</hi> craved a <hi>ſilence</hi> from my <hi>pen.</hi> Other conſiderations I had, that ſome <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> might befall them, by laying open theſe <hi>miſcarriages,</hi> which might have ſome <hi>reflexion</hi> on <hi>thoſe</hi> that have been leaſt <hi>culpable</hi> therein, if at all; And the <hi>regard</hi> I have of thoſe amongst them (who in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>integrity</hi> of their <hi>hearts,</hi> acted clearly for thoſe ends they were intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, receiving no worldly benefit thereby) hath much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed my purpoſe; Eſpecially, leaſt this Treatiſe might any wayes give offenſe to thoſe who are no <hi>titular Saints,</hi> but really <hi>godly,</hi> who count <hi>godlineſs gain,</hi> and not <hi>gain god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs;</hi> But I do cordially <hi>profeſs,</hi> I have no <hi>deſign</hi> of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice,</hi> nor do I bear the leaſt <hi>ill will</hi> to thoſe who are truly ſuch, but wiſh their number may be daily <hi>increaſed:</hi> That which moſt of all troubled me, was the <hi>conſideration</hi> I had of the uſe and <hi>advantage</hi> that the <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>Ill affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> perſons to the <hi>preſent Government</hi> would make of this
<pb facs="tcp:166287:4"/>
               <hi>diſcovery,</hi> againſt thoſe who <hi>attribute</hi> to themſelves the names of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>people</hi> of <hi>God;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Primam &amp; perpetuam eſse constat hiſtoriae legem, nihil falſi audere dicere nihil veri-non audere.</note>; All which, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſelf-<hi>intereſt</hi> and self-<hi>preſervation</hi> were no ſmall <hi>motives</hi> to blast the <hi>good intentions</hi> of the <hi>Author.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs finding no hopes of <hi>redreſs</hi> of the abuſes herein complained of; but on the contrary, it being viſible and apparent that their main <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>purpoſe</hi> was to root out all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> not only in <hi>Wales,</hi> but in <hi>England</hi> alſo; to leave the <hi>Churches empty,</hi> and with the fatneſs of the <hi>Tithes,</hi> and the fruits of other mens hard <hi>labours,</hi> to <hi>Propagate</hi> their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> not <hi>ſtumbling</hi> at <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge</hi> and <hi>Spirituall robbery,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Malach. 3.7, 8, 9, &amp; 10. verſes:</hi> And hating all perſons with a <hi>perfect hatred,</hi> who in the ſpirit of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>meekneſs,</hi> have friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>rebuked</hi> them, and <hi>minded</hi> them of theſe things; It was more then time for ſome <hi>good man</hi> to ariſe and ſtand up in the <hi>gap;</hi> who although <hi>Eliah</hi> may be miſtaken in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving he only was left, when the <hi>Lord</hi> had ſeven thouſand that had not <hi>bowed their knee to Baal, 1</hi> King. <hi>19.14, 18.</hi> He cannot (as he hopes) in theſe ſubſequent <hi>paſſages,</hi> which are too well known to the <hi>inhabitants,</hi> and all the Judges publique Officers of State, and other unbiaſſed ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who have travelled thoſe parts. And although this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe</hi> may offend ſome, yet ſince it is the <hi>cause</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who commands him to ſpeak theſe things, leaſt his <hi>people</hi> die for want of <hi>ſpiritual bread,</hi> whilest others ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet on the <hi>heavenly manna:</hi> he cannot, nor may not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the dictates of his <hi>conſcience,</hi> nor reſist the <hi>motions</hi> of his <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> chuſing rather to obey <hi>God</hi> then <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.29.</note> though to his own particular and private diſadvantage, counting worldly gain but <hi>loſſe,</hi> in <hi>competition</hi> with the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who doth with all humility acquieſce in his <hi>righteous judgement,</hi> hoping and waiting for a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>iſſue</hi> and ſucceſſe, according to his <hi>omnipotent</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:166287:5"/>
pleaſure, not doubting but the <hi>Lord</hi> will in his due time anſwer our expectations, in reſtoring the <hi>light</hi> of his <hi>Goſpel</hi> to thoſe that now ſit in <hi>darkneſſe</hi> and in the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of <hi>death;</hi> and will preſerve and continue the candlestick, where it is, and refreſh his diſtreſſed, oppreſſed people, with his ſpirituall joy and comfort; Which is the hearty wiſhes, prayers, and endeavours, and the main and only end of this Treatiſe, and the Author thereof</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M.C.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Some <hi>Errata</hi>'s have eſcaped the Printer in this haſtened Impreſſion, as <hi>Rogers</hi> for <hi>Roberts</hi> in many Copies at the end of the Marginall Notes, <hi>pag.</hi> 15. for <hi>winde</hi> r. <hi>come. pag.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 4. for <hi>expect</hi> r. <hi>exhibite. pag.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe and others may be eaſily corrected by the Pen of the candid Reader, at his largeſt leaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166287:5"/>
            <head>Mercurius Cambro-Britannicus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>R. <hi>Cradock,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor Powel,</hi> and others of their <hi>Tribe,</hi> having ſeriouſly conſidered of what great <hi>advantage</hi> it would prove unto them, in caſe they could obtain a power in themſelves and <hi>Colleagues,</hi> for diſpoſing of all <hi>Tythes, Glea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Impropriations,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues,</hi> in the thirteen Counties of <hi>Wales,</hi> conceived it the onely way to accompliſh their deſires,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To make the <hi>Parliament</hi> believe, that their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen were <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> and a People that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood nothing of God, or of the Power of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and ſo had need to be converted to the faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in order to this <hi>Converſion,</hi> they ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the <hi>Parliament</hi> to paſs an Act, called, <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Goſpel in</hi> Wales: And that for the better effecting and carrying on of thoſe ends propoſed by theſe Prieſts themſelves, and ſome others of their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Recommendation, ſubject to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſhould be named with them in the ſaid <hi>Act:</hi> And that to carry a greater countenance of Authority to the intended executioners thereof, ſeveral emminent and worthy Members of <hi>Parliament, Lawyers,</hi> and <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> ſhould be named in the Frontiſpiece thereof, well knowing, thoſe Gentlemen could not diſoblige their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Truſts and publique Imployments to act with theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> and their <hi>Confederates;</hi> ſo that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166287:6"/>
whole game ſhould be played by one intire party, which being acted ſo far diſtant from the cognizance of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> where the poor Inhabitants want <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> to ſtand for them, and repreſent their grievances to the Supreme Authority, they doubted not but to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their affairs in ſuch a way, as nothing ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ariſe in judgement againſt them in this world. And after ſerious debate and conſideration had, how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient it was to continue the old Miniſters in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective benefices, which if admitted, would ſwallow up the Tythes, and hinder the pretended <hi>Saints</hi> from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating their Eſtates: It was <hi>Reſolved</hi> upon the queſtion:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That for the better <hi>Propagation</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould be ejected and ſilenced, ſave only ſome of the moſt <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>illiterate</hi> of them, that would comply, and either farm their own Tythes, and accept of good bargains, or elſe accept of ſmall inconſiderable ſtipends.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And for the more formal ejection of the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that certain blank Articles of courſe, ſhould be drawn and applyed as an <hi>Engine</hi> to remove them from their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective charges and benefices. And for incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Informers</hi> and <hi>Deponents,</hi> that the <hi>Sequeſtrators</hi> ſhould offer good bargains of the <hi>Tythes</hi> to any that would come in, <hi>and help them to do the work of the Lord,</hi> for ſo they call the ruine and deſolation of the Miniſters and Miniſtry, and the extirpation of the Goſpel: And that certain Journey-men Pedlers, or Itinerant Tobacco-mongers, and others of like quality, ſhould perambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ſeveral of the Counties at 18<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>per diem,</hi> to make feigned diſcoveries of the pretended obliquities of the Miniſters, and return an accompt of their proceedings to the new Inquiſitors, otherwiſe called Sequeſtrators of the Tythes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166287:6"/>3. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the ſame courſe ſhould be uſed in the ejection of the <hi>School-Maſters,</hi> and that ſome of the Commiſſioners Clerks and Servants, that were in a capacity to read Engliſh, and make a warrant, ſhould be placed and ſtipended to ſpare charges, and the overplus of the moneys to go and relieve the poor diſtreſſe <hi>Saints.</hi> or the more needy number of the gathered Proſelytes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in order to the letting and ſetting of the Tythes, <hi>&amp;c. Reſolved,</hi> That certain grand <hi>Farmers</hi> or <hi>Sequeſtrators, Receivers</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> ſhould be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every County, choſen out of their <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Gad,</hi> and that they ſhould have power to let, ſet and diſpoſe of the ſame to the pretended <hi>godly party,</hi> or any of thoſe that have congregated themſelves for that purpoſe, at half the value or leſſer, and that none of the old Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or others of the <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> ſhould farm their own Tythes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at any rate, though they offered double the value paid by the pretended <hi>godly party.</hi> It being alſo reſolved, that none but thoſe that call themſelves <hi>Godly,</hi> ſhould live by, and feed of the Altar, it being a grand Tenet held by them, <hi>That thoſe onely who are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Righteous, ought to inherit the earth:</hi> And having taken into conſideration the great charges they would put themſelves unto, in caſe they ſhould ſupply every County with a competent number of <hi>godly, able, ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox preaching Ministers</hi> and <hi>Schoolmaſters,</hi> whoſe parts deſerving ſtipends accordingly, would leave too ſmal a remnant to relieve the pretended <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> they <hi>Reſolved:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That three or four <hi>Itinerary Teachers</hi> ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in moſt of the Counties, to ſupply the ſame, and becauſe it ſhall not ſeem too hard a work for ſso few to ſupply a whole County, which ſome of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt 120 Pariſhes, and the leaſt of 50 or 60. <hi>Reſolved</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166287:7"/>
alſo, That in their <hi>expedition,</hi> they ſhould be ſupplyed with freſh<note n="*" place="margin">Had they provided horſes for their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to, it had not been amiſs</note> horſes at every ſtage, which commonly are 10 or 20 miles, and ſometimes more, to ride poſt from place to place, to ſpread their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which for the moſt part conſiſts of theſe heads,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt all the old <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>School-Masters,</hi> and to perſwade the people, that their calling and miſſion was <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> and that all the<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs a bold univerſal challenge of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Valvaſor Powel, Iune</hi> 11 1652. ſent to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>George Griffith,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral letters thereupon, all publiſhed in print for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſatisfaction of the people, and vindication of the truth, and true intent of theſe Iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraries.</note> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of <hi>England</hi> were in the ſame condition; and that none ſhould be ſaved but <hi>Itineraries,</hi> or ſuch as ſhould liſt themſelves under them; and to gain credit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to what they taught, they declared, that this was the ſenſe of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that the ſame courſe ſhould be ſettled all <hi>England</hi> over, and all <hi>Parochial</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled <hi>Congregations</hi> ſhould be quite abrogated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To rail againſt the <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of the Law, and that they were all damned and accurſed, that would go to Law, either in the great <hi>Seſsions,</hi> or at <hi>Weſtminster</hi>-Hall; and that the <hi>Propagators</hi> were the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit perſons to decide all ſuits and differences: And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor Powel</hi> by name, did, and uſually doth in his invective Sermons, rail againſt and vilifie the Lawyers in general, more particularly at <hi>Llandſanferad in Elvel Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, in the County of Radnor, on the 25 of June laſt,</hi> when and where in his ſermon amongſt other railing expreſſions, he ſaid, That all the <hi>Lawyers</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> were worſe then <hi>Theeves</hi> or <hi>Pick-purſos,</hi> and that there were but two or three honeſt Lawyers in all the <hi>Nation,</hi> where he was ſo beſet by ſome of his own <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and ſo whipt with arguments by thoſe ſpirits which he himſelf firſt raiſed, who for three hours ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166287:7"/>
againſt the doctrine then taught by him; in ſo much that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Methinks M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Valvaſor</hi> you ſhould have bred up your ſcholars to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manners; But the old Proverb is herein verified, <hi>Trim Tram, Like Maſter, like man.</hi>
               </note> made a hard ſhift to get from them to his retirement, which made the Gentleman very ſick next morning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all thoſe that were not liſted of their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations, were little better then <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> and perſons that were out of the Pale of the Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That all thoſe Miniſters that did formerly preach and officiate, were only formall Teachers and Learned men; and therefore declared <hi>humane Learning</hi> to be the greateſt obſtructor of the work of <hi>Propagation,</hi> and that acquired Learning is an<note n="*" place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>W. Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> at <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steigne.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eſsential part and limb of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That all thoſe Miniſters that ſhould either Preach, Pray or ſpeak any thing againſt this work of <hi>Propagation,</hi> were enemies to the godly party, and uncapable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying their fifths, though allowed their wives by the ſaid Act of <hi>Propagation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That all thoſe that were not liſted of their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations (or rather <hi>Martiall Troops</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies to execute the commands of theſe ſtone-Prieſts, who ride them like Mules and Aſſes) were incapable of bearing any Office or place of Truſt in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and the like Tranſactions being the ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the work of <hi>Propagation in Wales,</hi> which now hath reigned nigh three years, I now behold <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> decaied, and the light of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> almoſt quite extinguiſhed there, the poor ejected Miniſters with their wives and families ready to periſh, particular perſons enriched, and the pretended <hi>godly party</hi> in new Dreſſes and Attires, having changed their poor <hi>Friza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> for rich <hi>Scarlet</hi> and <hi>Pluſh,</hi> that would make <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf to <hi>bluſh</hi> to ſee this ſudden alteration. New
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166287:8"/>
ſumptous, coſtly houſes are built and erected, great purchaſes made; ſome that were born but to 7<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a year, become puchaſers of <hi>Lordſhips</hi> and <hi>Mannors</hi> of above 1000<hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
               <hi>per annum;</hi> and all ſtriving who ſhall outvy and outbid the other in their purchaſes; witneſs thoſe hot incounters at the Box, in <hi>Worceſter</hi> houſe, <hi>Drury</hi> houſe, <hi>Gurney</hi> houſe, and other places; ſome purchaſing in their own names; others more ſubtle, in their friends and ſervants names. The Gentry and all the conſiderable perſons of <hi>Wales</hi> dejected and oppreſſed, ready to ſell the remnant of their eſtates to come and inhabit in <hi>England,</hi> being not able to live in this ſad, dark, oppreſſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their Country is brought unto: And if this Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be once ſetled in <hi>England,</hi> good Lord where ſhall we then fly for ſuccour, but unto thee? Great thoughts of heart and heart-burnings amongſt all ſorts of people, who are ſadly aggrieved to pay their Tithes more ſtrictly then ever they did, and yet have neither Preaching, Praying, Chriſtening, decent Burials, or other ſpiritual Rights or Comforts adminiſtred unto them; and finding no hopes of redreſſe or relief herein (all addreſſes to the <hi>Propagators,</hi> as in other caſes, ſo in theſe, proving fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.) The inhabitants of the ſix Counties of South-<hi>Wales,</hi> and County of <hi>Monmouth</hi> reſolved to make their humble ſuit <hi>to the Supream Power of the Nation, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> by Petition, ſetting forth the Heads and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of theſe their grievances, praying that great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to take ſome courſe for the future ſupply of their Country with ſuch a competent number of Godly, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Orthodox Miniſters and School-Maſters, ſuch as the Parliament ſhould approve of: And for an Account of the Profits of the Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> received for the two laſt years, in the ſaid ſeven Counties, charged to be worth 20000<hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
               <hi>per annum</hi> and upwards. Whereupon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166287:8"/>
the <hi>Parliament</hi> out of their pious inclination to advance <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and in order to a Redreſs of the ſaid ſad grievances complained of in the Petition, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſame to the Honourable Committee of <hi>Plundered Miniſters,</hi> with Power for them to ſend for Perſons, Papers and Witneſſes, and examine on Oath, and Iſſue forth Commiſſions to the Country (where the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and matters of fact do lye and ariſe) to examine Witneſſes touching any of the matters contained in the Petition, and to return thoſe Examinations to the ſaid Committee, who were thereupon to ſtate matter of fact, and Report the ſame to the Parliament. Which ſad news coming to the knowledge of the pretended <hi>Godly party</hi> in <hi>Wales;</hi> It was reſolved by the <hi>Itinerant Synod (nemine contradicente)</hi> as followeth,</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Petitioning the Parliament without their leaves and permiſſion, was a high breach of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Godly party.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Petitioning the Parliament for ſupply of <hi>Godly, Able, Orthodox Ministers</hi> and <hi>School-Maſters,</hi> ſuch as the Parliament ſhould approve of, was a high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the Act of <hi>Propagation,</hi> and that ſuch the Petitioners deſires and intentions ſhould be declared, conſtrued and expounded, and ſo rendred by them to the Parliament, to be a petitioning for the <hi>reſtauration</hi> of <hi>Malignant, Drunken, Unpreaching, ejected Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Witnes thoſe ſeveral ſpeeches and expreſſions delivered at the Committee of Plundered Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; <hi>March</hi> 16, <hi>May</hi> 18. &amp; 21. where and when the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words and true meaning of the Petition &amp; Petitioners were moſt groſſely miſrepreſented. Where M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Peters,</hi> uncalled, unſent for, and unconcerned, did voluntarily declare all the Miniſters of <hi>Wales</hi> to be drunken, debauched, ignorant and illiterate, not fit to be truſted to keep a kennell of Hounds, or a dozen of Sheep. Are theſe words becoming a holy man, Archbiſhop and Metropolitan of <hi>England?</hi> or do they become a ſober man and one that owns the Name of a Chriſtian, to traduce his brethren in general, many whereof of he never ſaw, having only travelled <hi>Pembrokeſhire,</hi> and ſojourned at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Lort's</hi> for a ſhort time: and what good he did in thoſe parts, with an anſwer to theſe his unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian expreſſions, there will ſhortly come forth a Paper from one of thoſe he traduced, to let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Peters</hi> know they are not ſo illiterate and ignorant as he would render them.</note>.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:166287:9"/>8. That to call the pretended <hi>Godly party</hi> to account for any thing by them received, for which they ought to be accountable to the State, to be a ſowing of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt the <hi>Parliament of England ſitting at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and the <hi>moving Aſsembly of Wales.</hi> And that all the Contrivers, Subſcribers and Promoters of the ſaid Petition, and Agents therein imployed, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt as diſturbers of the peace of the pretented <hi>Saints,</hi> and obſtructing them in their receiving the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Revenue of the Church in peace, and that they ſhould be proceeded againſt as <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents,</hi> and diſaffected perſons to the proceedings of the pretended Godly party in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor Powell,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cradock,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Jenkin Jones,</hi> and all the wandring Prieſts and <hi>Goſpel Poſtmaſters</hi> in <hi>South-Wales</hi> ſhould ride Poſt from County to County, and Pariſh to Pariſh, to threaten all the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners and their Agents with <hi>damnation, Sequeſtration</hi> and <hi>ruine.</hi> Nevertheleſs with this <hi>Salva Conſcientia,</hi> that thoſe that would repent by denying their hands, and diſowning the Petition, ſhould be taken into their conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and favourably entertained.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That all the reſidue of the ancient Divines and unejected Miniſters in <hi>South-Wales</hi> ſhould be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſilenced, and neither to have liberty to Preach, Pray, Adminiſter the Sacraments, Bury the dead, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or viſit the ſick, or Officiate or perform any other charitable and Chriſtian work, leaſt they ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote or advance the Petition. And the better to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ejected Miniſters wives and families, that they ſhould be turned all out from their houſes and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, to travell into ſome other <hi>Forreign Plantation,</hi> to <hi>propagate</hi> there; and for their incouragement in their voyage, that the Fifths allowed their wives by the Act
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166287:9"/>
of <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſhould thereafter be kept back from them, and that they ſhould, as in the Primitive times, carry neither <hi>Scrip</hi> nor <hi>Wallett,</hi> but only live by the Alms and Charitable benevolence of the people.</p>
            <p>Information being given by one of the gadly Scouts, that <hi>North-Wales</hi> were reſolved to take good courage and example by <hi>South-Wales,</hi> and were preparing the like humble addreſs to the Parliament, ſetting forth the work of propagation there.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor Powell</hi> do ride Poſt to <hi>North-Wales,</hi> to inform the inhabitants there, That the Parliament had declared the Petition of <hi>South-Wales, Scandalous</hi> and <hi>Seditious,</hi> and that all the ſubſcribers and promoters thereof ſhould be ſequeſtred and proceeded againſt as enemies to the Parliament and preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and to threaten all thoſe that ſhould ſubſcribe or promote the like Petition there, with Damnation, Sequeſtration and ruine, which falſe Allarum hath in ſome meaſure obſtructed the inhabitants of <hi>North-Wales</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nevertheleſs all <hi>North-Wales</hi> are very active and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an humble addreſſe to the Parliament, ſetting forth the myſtery of the Work of Propagation there, which will be ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſented by perſons of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, and of known worth and integrity to the Parliament and preſent Government.</note>, from repreſenting the Parliament with the true ſtate of their Country, in relation to the propagation of the Goſpel there, and made M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor Powell</hi> Print his Letter in the Frontiſpiece of a Diurnall come out very lately, to undertake to give the Parliament an exact account of <hi>North-Wales,</hi> and the propagation there, wherein he goes about to confute the Petition of <hi>South-Wales,</hi> and all that is there declared, he undertakes to make good <hi>upon the word of a Christian, and a Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister.</hi> A bold and high preſumption, and too hard a task for him to perform: And a ſober man would count it little better then madneſs in a profeſſed Chriſtian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to undertake to make good and juſtifie the actions of all thoſe perſons intruſted therein, which are many, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom it is not very unlikely but ſome miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166287:10"/>
               <note place="margin">I wiſh M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> may be able to juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and I ſhall make bold to minde him of his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt old <hi>Hugh Lloid</hi> in <hi>Breckon</hi> in impriſoning &amp; keeping him there without Bayl or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, untill he paid him 100<hi rend="sup">l</hi>, &amp; this done on a bare Arreſt, which proved to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Powell</hi> an effectual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, for none durſt Bail him. And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers more of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Powels</hi> pranks that might be inſtanced.</note> may be; for there were but twelve Apoſtles, and yet amongſt them one <hi>Judas.</hi> But this I obſerve by him, he hath dealt friendly with his Countreymen in <hi>North-Wales,</hi> who cals all their Miniſters and Teachers, <hi>Such as have not the power of Godlineſs, and very few the form thereof, or that have been firm and faithfull to the Parliament, but moſt of them unpreaching Curats, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in their lives,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein he learns of the ſcolds at <hi>Billinſgate,</hi> to cry whore firſt: but I leave that Letter, or rather M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Powels Creed</hi> (for it runs all on beliefs and hearſaies) to be anſwered and unfolded by ſome of his own Countrymen<note n="*" place="margin">Reade M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Griffiths</hi> Letters, and a ſober Reply to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Powels</hi> Paper againſt the Petition lately Printed.</note>: But this i'le tell him by the way, that if he preacheth no more truth in his Pulpit, then he halth broached in Print, I ſhould be ſorry to ride Poſt with him up and down the Country to hear him Preach, for the beſt bargain that he hath procured to the holieſt of his friends.</p>
            <p>But the Gent, would fain make you believe that this Propagation in <hi>Wales</hi> will laſt long, and therefore recites next his <hi>Creed,</hi> certain Propoſals, tending to bring in the like <hi>Propagation</hi> all <hi>England</hi> over. Well done M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> will not the <hi>Tithes</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> ſerve you and your friends, but you muſt creep into <hi>England</hi> to ſhare of the fruits of their labour alſo? But certainly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor</hi> would be ſatisfied with the Tithes of <hi>Wales,</hi> if he were ſure the Trade of <hi>Tithe-gathering</hi> would long continue there, but he thinks that the <hi>Act of Propagation in Wales</hi> hath but a ſhort time to live, expiring the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> next, unleſs it be ſupported and continued, by procuring the like Act over all <hi>England;</hi> for his Countrymen are very angry that this way of <hi>Propagation of the Goſpel</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:166287:10"/>
ſhould be practiſed only amongſt them, and that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould be ſupplied with a competent number of <hi>Godly, Able, Orthodox Schoolmaſters</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> Surely <hi>Wales</hi> do conceive that the <hi>Parliament</hi> are as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound and concerned to provide for the ſupply of their <hi>ſpiritual neceſsities,</hi> as for <hi>England;</hi> eſpecially if it be true what the promoters of the <hi>Act,</hi> and the perſons that reap the benefit thereof did inform the <hi>Parliament, That their Country doth abound with ignorance and prophanneſſe.</hi> But hold M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Valvaſor,</hi> they are not ſo ignorant but they can ſee who thoſe <hi>Rats</hi> are that eat up their <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Caterpillers</hi> that devour the fruit of their labours.</p>
            <p>Information being given that that ever to be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gent. Coll. <hi>Edward Freeman,</hi> Attorney Generall for the Commonwealth in <hi>South-Wales,</hi> and a Gentleman that hath hazarded his life and fortune to ſerve the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> was intruſted as Counſellour for the Petitioners; It was <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That all the Itineraries ſhould publiquely Preach in all places againſt the Law, and all the profeſſors thereof, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially againſt Collonel <hi>Freeman;</hi> and that their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers ſhould be to the Lord, to puniſh him in his perſon, power, and in his place<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Valvaſor Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> in his inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Sermon before the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at <hi>Preſteign</hi> Seſſions laſt. It is no great wonder that he would rail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Collonel <hi>Freeman,</hi> when he durſt call the States of <hi>Holland</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, drunkards, and wiſh them to go home with this Anſwer, That Sion is built; beſides other words by him uſed, tending to the ſcandal and diſhonour of the Nation and civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Well done <hi>Valvaſor,</hi> to ingage two States in a bloudy, cruel War againſt one another, to the hazard of both Nations, which all the Holy-water wherein he dips his liſted Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregators cannot appeaſe, unleſs God in his mercy do it, maugre the endeavours of theſe Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands. <hi>Factet ſe miles glorioſus oratorem potentem, quoad hoc ſaltem vix ſe praebuit prudentem,</hi> V.P.</note>. And ſhortly after Collonel <hi>Freeman</hi> falling ſick of a Fever and Pluraſie, after a dinner made at <hi>Cardiff,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. It was likewiſe <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That publique thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving ſhould be given to the Lord in all the particular ſeparated Congregation in <hi>Wales,</hi> for hearing the prayers of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:166287:11"/>Information being alſo given, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gunter</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Roberts</hi> (perſons of known integrity to the Parliament and preſent Government, and ſo had been from the very beginning of the late Wars to this day) were imp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyed Agents by the Countrey, to agitate for them in their abſence, in relation to the ſaid Petition; and to uſe their utmoſt endeavors to give a right information to the Parliament and Committee of plundered Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, of the ſtate of the Countrey, whereby to draw it to an iſſue and examination, that the truth might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by teſtimonies of witneſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Watkins,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lewis,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Creede, Shony Morgan, Hugh Rogers,</hi> and others of the beſt Beagles, ſhould be imployed to hunt dryfoot, to finde ſome Articles againſt Col: <hi>Freeman,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs thoſe frivolous falſe, ſcandals Articles exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited before the Lords Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, by that Spawn of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <hi>vix credo,</hi> by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the ſtony Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory in <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall.</hi>
               </note> Mr <hi>Gunter,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Roberts,</hi> if poſſible, to cloud and eclipſe them, and render them odious to the Parliament, hoping by this means to deter them from acting for the Petitioners, according to their conſciences, and the truſt repoſed in them, or elſe to blemiſh the good intentions of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners: But the Gentlemen for their integrity are ſo well known to Members of Parliament, and all their Countrey in general, that their endeavors hitherto have proved fruitleſs, and their progreſs therein cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them ſucceſs, if the Gentlemen have equal right and justice done them.</p>
            <p>And for the better carrying on of this their <hi>deſign, Reſolved</hi> alſo, That means be uſed as well by the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit knockers,</hi> as by the <hi>Dreadful Sequeſtrators,</hi> to force ſome of the Petitioners to deny their hands, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Petition: And that it ſhould be ſpoken at the Committee, how eaſie it is for one Welſhman to ſubſcribe another Welſhmans hand<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, intituled, <hi>An humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wales, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, <hi>for the bleſſed work of Propagation there,</hi> preſented the Parliament in <hi>June,</hi> 1651. by the chief perſons that reap the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of this great work of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed by 19000. 18000. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of never ſaw or heard of it. A pretty knack to blinde the eyes of the Parliament, and abuſe the poor Countrey.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:166287:11"/>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That all poſſible means be uſed to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept all Letters betwixt the Petitioners in the Countrey, and their Agents in <hi>London,</hi> to prevent a true informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and repreſentation to the Parliament, of the ſad grievances of the Countrey; and to that purpoſe, orders were given at<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs the intercepting of the very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al directions of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Haberdaſhers Hall ſent down to Mr. <hi>Harard,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> their ſub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, and divers other papers of publique and private concernment, all letters being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and ſuch onely intercepted, which made diſcoveries of the good proceedings of the godly party in <hi>Wales:</hi> A pretty way to prevent a true information to be given to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their bleſſed doings in <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hereford, Monmouth,</hi> and all other places, inſomuch that the Petitioners and their Agents could not with ſafety write any Letters to or fro, either by the Poſt or Carryer, or any private Meſſengers.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was alſo informed, That the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners did make a voluntary contribution to defray the charges of Counſellors Fees, and other neceſſary charges incident to the proſecution of ſo weighty and neceſſary a buſineſs, as a Petition from ſeven Counties, which concerned the ſalvation of their ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That it ſhould be conſtrued and declared to be a raiſing of moneys to levy War againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and preſent Government; and that <hi>Hugh Rogers</hi> a quondam arrant Cavalier in Arms for the late King, but lately converted, and others of the parties concerned, ſhould exhibit an information<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide,</hi> The fooliſh, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited before the Committee of plundered Miniſters, wherein Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi> and his confederates (meaning the Petitioners, are charged with framing, contriving and ſubſcribing the Petition, which he deſires may be put in a way of examination: Good Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> you may ſpare this labor, for the Petitioners and Subſcribers have, do and will own it, and Mr. <hi>Gunter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> as their Sollicitors or Agents, with others intruſted therein, act publiquely, and will never deny the Petition, or renounce their honeſt, pious and Chriſtian appearance, in their civil proſecution and mannagement thereof.</note> in the name of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>godly party,</hi> againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hugh Gunter</hi> and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates (for ſo he is pleaſed to call the Petitioners) of a dangerous deſign in all <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> to obſtruct the Trade of <hi>Tyth-gathering,</hi> which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> deſires may be <hi>univerſall</hi> over all <hi>England,</hi> as well as <hi>Wales.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:166287:12"/>
               <hi>Well done</hi> Hugo <hi>to complain first, leſt your quondam Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiering Trade, and your late Actions in your under Sherifft altry be ript up, to manifeſt your holineſs, but all will not do, you muſt winde to it at laſt with the reſt of your late converted Brethren, who finde Tyth-gathering a more ſafe beneficial and ſweeter trade, then plundering of the Parliamenteers, and the well-affected party, from whom your noodle received ſore knocks for your ſawcineſs; and have ſince your pretended Converſion, gained more by your ſeeming ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, then ever you did by pillage under the power of the late King.</hi> And whereas one of the pretended godly party had abuſed one Captain <hi>Jones,</hi> who is a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that was always faithful to the Parliament, and bore Arms for them in the firſt and ſecond War, yet was by the procurement of one of the ſuppoſed <hi>Saints,</hi> and the aſſiſtance of ſome of the grand Cavaliers there (with other Gentlemen of quality well affected to the Parliament) cruelly impriſoned at <hi>Cardiff,</hi> without a Charge or Articles proved material to warrant the ſame, who deſiring civil ſatisfaction for his wrongs ſuffered, and demanding a reaſon why he ſhould be ſo dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and ſo ill rewarded for his former good ſervices to the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the pretended <hi>godly party,</hi> were in danger of their lives; and that this was the beginning of levying War againſt the <hi>gadly.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Titular Saints</hi> could not ſufficiently Tyrannize over the Inhabitants, nor carry on their gainful deſigns without Troops of Horſe, and Companies of Foot in each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which would alſo bring good gain to the Officers and Souldiers<note n="*" place="margin">Well done <hi>Jammy,</hi> this is a wel contrived plot to inlarge your pover and propagate your eſtates, by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your poor Countrey, by drawing a needleſs charge and trouble upon them.</note>.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That a Letter be written by the <hi>gadly party,</hi> and the particular Congregations in <hi>Southwales,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166287:12"/>
directed to the <hi>ſtony Gallery in</hi> Whitehall, to move the Councel of State, that certain Gentlemen,<note n="*" place="margin">Have you not already oppreſſed them ſufficiently with falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments in <hi>Cardiff,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, grounded on your own feigned ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions and falſe informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, firſt lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the plot, then diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and making the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſuffer? have you more of theſe Devices in ſtore in your Black Budget?</note> who had ſubſcribed the Petition, ſhould be therefore brought up by ſpecial Meſſengers before them, to anſwer why they ſubſcribed the Petition, and do go about to call the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God</hi> to an accompt: And that for the future ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>gadly party</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> ſome Commiſſions ſhould iſſue down to ſome of the <hi>gadly,</hi> to raiſe Horſe and Foot to carry in the Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their Barns and Store-houſes, their own horſes being unable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſo great a ſervice, and the Pariſhioners ſo malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that they refuſe to lend their aſſiſtance therein, ſince they cannot Farm their own Tythes at any rate, although they offer twice as much for the ſame as it is now let at. But the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>State</hi> had other affairs of greater concernment, and ſo adjourned the buſineſs till further time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the like Letter be written to put all theſe Gentlement that had ſubſcribed the Petition, out of the <hi>Commiſsion of Peace,</hi> the <hi>Act of Aſſeſsments,</hi> and all other places of truſt and imployment; the Ambulatory Aſſembly at <hi>Swanzy</hi> having declared them uncapable to bear any office or truſt in the Commonwealth: Which <hi>Reſolve</hi> was in part executed, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gwin,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walbeith,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Havard,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Lloyd</hi> (though perſons well-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Parliament, and of conſiderable fortunes) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately put out of the <hi>Commiſsion of Peace</hi> in <hi>Breckon</hi> ſhire, and ſeveral other Gentlemen in other Counties, without Articles, Proofs or Examinations to ſhew any cauſe for it, except onely for ſubſcribing the Petition; and that it was the deſire of the pretended <hi>godly party</hi> it ſhould be ſo, and divers other Gentlemen put out of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166287:13"/>
Commiſſions in other Counties, and ſeveral inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate inferior perſons placed in their rooms, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Authority, and apparent wrong and oppreſſion of the Countrey. <hi>The Committee of Plundered Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> having read the Petition and <hi>Reſolves of Parliament,</hi> did order the <hi>Propagators</hi> of <hi>Southwales</hi> to Anſwer the Petition, and bring in their Accompt by the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> laſt, which put the <hi>Welſh</hi> Saints to a pittiful cold ſwet, in riding up and down, and ſetting up day and night to patch up their broken accompts: And though they had ſeveral private and publique meetings for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, all produced by the 18 of <hi>May</hi> but a ſheet of paper, and a few general negatives<note n="*" place="margin">Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, there was a Book fairly written, with a hanſom title to it, produced before the Committee of plundered Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read nor lodged there, whereby copies thereof might be had, and the Petitioners enabled to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the ſame (as is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in all other caſes relating to accompts). But the curtain was no ſooner drawn to ſhew this fair picture but as ſoon withdrawn, it being unſafe to leave matters of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to publique view: So that the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get a copy thereof to this day, it being reſolved by the Saints to make their Accompts at the laſt day of judgement.</note> therein contained, with a confeſſion of 20000<hi rend="sup">l</hi> or thereabouts, received for the two laſt years, but never ſay out of what received in particular, whether they made or received, or might have made or received more of the Tythes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor do they expreſs what is become of the 20000<hi rend="sup">l</hi> nor how they have diſpoſed of the ſum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor expreſs any thing in paticular. It being <hi>Reſolved</hi> at <hi>Swanzy,</hi> as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to ſave their credit, to put in a few generals, ſtuffed up with a parcel of godly words, to make ſome pretence and ſhew to the world what good ſtewards they have been, it being dangerous and unſafe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a particular Accompt, leaſt there ſhould come a particular ſurcharge, and after that, which is worſe, a Commiſſion to prove it: And though one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagators confeſſed there was a particular anſwer and accompt in Town, and in their abſence ſhewed, yet the Petitioners could not obtain that favor as to have it brought in, nor ſo much as a Copy of that general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt remaining with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Phelps,</hi> until the 16 of <hi>July</hi> after their particulars put in; but inſtead thereof, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166287:13"/>
Petitioners required to bring in within two days after, ſuch particulars contained in their Petition, upon which they did deſire to examine witneſſes: The Petitioners not conceiving that they ſhould be required to exhibite any new charge, not required, ordered or directed by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, did accordingly inſiſt on all the particular heads of the Petition, and offered to prove the ſame, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular and ſillable thereof, ſo as they might have (according to the Reſolves of Parliament) a Commiſſion to the Countrey to examine where their witneſſes, and matters of fact do lie, the neareſt to <hi>Weſtminster</hi> being an 100 miles, and ſome 200 miles diſtant, which was all as they conceived was their duty to do, or could be required or expected according to thoſe Reſolves.</p>
            <p n="21">21. But it ſeems the goodly party have prayed they might not accompt, and ſo reſolved at their general Meeting, whoſe prayers prevailed, in ſo much that the Petitioners cannot proceed to iſſue or prove their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſs they will follow the example of Coll: <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> in naming perſons and crimes, and particular miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, and make way for taking ſhipping to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> or to a worſer place, for of neceſſity the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners muſt needs do ſo by offending ſuch as do not love to be told of their faults, or elſe confine themſelves to a few particulars, beyond which they may not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſo leave the whole truth of the Petition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examined: And if it ſhould be expected, that the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners ſhould name all thoſe perſons that have acted by vertue of the Act of <hi>Propagation,</hi> and received and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of the Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the qualities and parts of the preſent ſtipended Itineraries and Schoolmaſters, with their number and ſtipends, and by whom paid, and where all the moneys and profits received are lodged, with all the particular miſdemeanors, neglects and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166287:14"/>
in their not executing, and undue executing of the powers given by the ſaid Acts (as it ſeems the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the particulars mentioned in the order of the 18 of <hi>May</hi> laſt was rendred by ſome perſons concerned.) It would be in the firſt place a work of impoſſibility, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be done in two days, as was ordered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. 2. A work of apparent danger to the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners. 3. A clear advantage to the Propagators, and a means to avoid a true examination of the matters contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Petition; wherefore the Petitioners are reſolved to preſent the Parliament with another Petition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to know their pleaſures, Whether truth may be made evident as againſt the <hi>Propagators &amp; Tythe-gatherers?</hi> 2. Whether thoſe that call themſelves <hi>The godly party,</hi> are lyable to accompt? 3. Whether the Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now impoſed on the Nation, eſpecially poor, diſtreſſed, oppreſſed <hi>Wales,</hi> be ſo light and eaſie to be born, and the Countrey ſo well able to undergo them, and the publique Treaſury ſo full, as that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will ſuffer a Revenue of 20000 l <hi>per annum</hi> and more received for two years and upward, to go to the hands of particular private perſons, to build new ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous houſes, and buy lands without any enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſum, or elſe will looſe 20000 l <hi>per annum de fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo,</hi> for the Tythes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the inhabitants, who are ready to give ſecurity for that purpoſe, if the Parliament will grant it within two years, comes to 20000 l more then the Propagators have accompted in their general anſwer for the two laſt years, which if once granted, will eaſe the Propagators and Tythe-gatherers of a great deal of pains; care and trouble; and leave them to their <hi>Divine Exerciſes,</hi> who have little leaſure now to attend thoſe <hi>Holy duties,</hi> performable by thoſe that attribute to themſelves the names of <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>People of God,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166287:14"/>
then it will appear to the whole world, whether they ſerve God for <hi>gain or godlineſs ſake:</hi> and by this means the ſtate cannot be defrauded, for it will be apparent what is paid out of the Tithes towards the Propagation of the Goſpel, and maintenance of Schools, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Act, when there are particular perſons that are <hi>Farmers,</hi> and particular perſons that are <hi>Propagators,</hi> whoſe ſeveral Accounts, paiments and disburſments, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, will ſoon diſcover how the State hath been dealt withall the two laſt years, which can never be done when the ſame perſons are Farmors, Collectors, Tithe gatherers and Propagators; ſo that it is eaſie, without examination of the truth where matter of fact doth ariſe, and where all particulars have been acted, to blinde the eyes of the Parliament with a generall, plauſible anſwer, made up of <hi>Godly words;</hi> as one of the <hi>Itineraries</hi> anſwered an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers wife in <hi>Monmouthſhire</hi> near <hi>Uske,</hi> After he and his company had drunk all her drink, ſhe called for money for the reckoning, ſhe was anſwered by the holy man, That the <hi>Saints carry neither ſilver nor gold, nor ſcrip nor wallet:</hi> but the poor woman replied, that ſhe could not ſatisfie her Landlord for his Mault with a <hi>Scripture phraſe:</hi> no more can godly words ſatisfie the defect of the Preaching of the Goſpel, and want of Miniſters and Schoolmaſters, nor maintain Armies, and Navies, or eaſe the poor Country of their Taxations and Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: It being a ſad thing to ſee ſo great a Revenue real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended by the Parliament, to be converted according to the Act to be ſo ill imployed, and no accompt rendered for it; when the Pariſhioners and Inhabitants cannot Farm their own Tithes at any reaſonable rate, though they are ready to give double the rate, the ſame are let out to the chief Farmers. Their uſuall courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to grant one, two or more Churches to one of the gadly party, or other perſon that is liſted of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166287:15"/>
Congregation at leſſe then half the value. This Grandfarmer, or holy man, hath ſeverall Subfarmours and Subtenants under him, who let out the Tithes at the rack rent and utmoſt peny they can make of the ſame to the great oppreſſion and diſcontent of the Inhabitants, and the apparent wrong and prejudice of the State. And becauſe all theſe tranſactions herein before declared, may not ſeem to ſtrangers for a Romanſe or a falſe ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Libell, or Information (as undoubtedly the <hi>Goodly party</hi> will endeavour to render it) the Petitioners of the ſix Counties of <hi>South Wales</hi> and County of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> have prepared ſeverall particulars of the true State of the ſaid Counties, in relation to the work of Propagation of the Goſpel there, grounded on their Petition, which on the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> inſtant, were offered and exhibited to the conſideration of the Honourable Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for Plundered Miniſters, which they are ready to prove and make good, and much more, if enabled by Commiſſioners to be iſſued to the Country, where matter of fact ariſeth, and witneſſes, reſide, according to the former Reſolves of Parliament in that behalf, which Committee ordered the ſame ſhould be Reported to the Parliament, whereby Commiſſions may iſſue out for a clear diſcovery of the truth thereof, in order to a Religious Reformation of all theſe abuſes, the ſequell whereof I do promiſe to give you in my next. And for the further ſatisfaction of the Parliament and Nation, how well the Inhabitants of <hi>South-Wales</hi> are dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by theſe goodly perſons intruſted with the <hi>Military and Civil Government there;</hi> It is ſhortly intended to come forth an abſtract of their late proceedings in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the powers given them, as <hi>Committee of Indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Arbitrary Commiſsioners. Commiſsioners of the monethly Aſſeſsment. Commiſsioners of Sequeſtration. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of Militia</hi> and <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> &amp;c. which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166287:15"/>
will be, not only averred but proved by thoſe that deſire to give the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> a true accompt of the ſad Conſequents that befell thoſe parts of this Nation, ſince ſome perſons have been intruſted there, with the execution of the ſeverall powers aforeſaid, to this end only, <hi>That ſome timely information may be given the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority of the Nation, the Parliament of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of England,</hi> hereafter to be more wary and cautious who they truſt, and with what <hi>Powers</hi> ſo farre diſtant from their <hi>Cognizance;</hi> The <hi>Inhabitants</hi> having ſo few <hi>Repreſentatives in Parliament</hi> to ſpeak for them; their main and only end therein being to prevent future miſchiefs and inconveniences that may befall the <hi>preſent Government,</hi> and more particularly the <hi>Inhabitants of Wales,</hi> and univerſally the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> by the undue and indirect execution of theſe good and wholeſome <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Authorities</hi> that are or ſhall be given by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the advancement of <hi>Gods glory,</hi> and the <hi>well Government</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that every one may in peace enjoy his own, and receive incouragement to wiſh well and cordially affect the <hi>preſent Government,</hi> and faithfully ingage for the defence thereof in the injoyment of true <hi>Religion, wholeſome Laws,</hi> and <hi>just Liberties and Freedoms,</hi> which are the Birthright and Inheritance of the people: The Enlargement, Eſtabliſhment and long Continuance thereof being the occaſion of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the hearty wiſhes and prayers of.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Englands, (but more particularly <hi>Wales</hi>) moſt faithfull and cordial Well-wiſher M. C. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
